Arlington, Mass. Pleasant Street Congregational Church records, 1842-2010.
Congregational Library Archives
Arlington, Mass. Pleasant Street Congregational Church records, 1842-2010.
RG4962
Congregational Library Archives
4.71 Cubic Feet
(5 boxes)
Pleasant Street Congregational Church was organized in December 1842, as the Orthodox Congregational Church of West Cambridge. Many of the original members of the Orthodox Congregational Church had been members of the First Congregational Church in Arlington but left when the church turned Unitarian in 1828. Between 1940 and 1953, Orthodox Congregational Church was renamed Pleasant Street Congregational Church. The church would officially close its doors in early 2011. This collection contains numerous records from Pleasant Street Congregational church, including as vital statistics, committee records and meetings, minister information, auxiliary information and events, printed materials and annual reports, church finances, church building information and a variety of photographs.
Bradshaw, Anna, 1785-1869
Bushnell, Samuel Clarke, 1852-1930
Orthodox Congregational Church (Arlington, Mass.)
Pleasant Street Congregational Church (Arlington, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Pleasant Street Congregational Church of Arlington, Massachusetts in May 2011; 2014-23.
Historical Note
Pleasant Street Congregational Church was organized in December 1842, as the Orthodox Congregational Church of West Cambridge. Many of the original members of the Orthodox Congregational Church had been members of the First Congregational Church in Arlington but left when the church turned Unitarian in 1828. Anna Bradshaw (1785-1869) played an important role in founding this church by holding the early prayer meetings on her homestead. The parcel of land on which the church was erected was donated by Anna Bradshaw. The church steeple was destroyed by a tornado in 1871 and it was again damaged during a hurricane in 1938. Between 1940 and 1953, Orthodox Congregational Church was renamed Pleasant Street Congregational Church. By 1963, Pleasant Street Congregational Church had joined the United Church of Christ. In April, 2010, a Merger Action Team was formed to explore a merger with the Congregational Church of West Medford, UCC. Within the next year, the church would officially close.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains numerous records from Pleasant Street Congregational church, including as vital statistics, committee records and meetings, minister information, auxiliary information and events, printed materials and annual reports, church finances, church building information and a variety of photographs.
Arrangement
The Pleasant Street Congregational Church records are arranged into three series and seven subseries. Furthermore, each series and subseries is arranged by date.
Series 1: Church records, 1842-2010
Subseries 1: Vital records, 1842-1960
Subseries 2: Committee records and meetings, 1842-2009
Subseries 3: Ministers, 1878-1989
Subseries 4: Auxiliary Organizations and events, 1899, 1937-2010
Subseries 5: Historical information, 1901-2004
Subseries 6: Printed materials, 1901-2007
Subseries 7: Annual reports, 1932-2010
Series 2: Financial records, 1855-1998
Series 3: Photographs, 1871-1999
Related Materials
Additional materials related to Arlington, Mass Congregational Church can be found at the Arlington Historical Society and the Arlington Public Library.
Church architecture -- Designs and plans.; Church bells.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Installation (clergy).; Marriage records.; Obituaries.; Scrapbooks.; Arlington (Mass.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Photographs.; Arlington (Mass.) -- Church history.; Orthodox Congregational Church (Arlington, Mass.); Pleasant Street Congregational Church (Arlington, Mass.)
- Church records, 1842 2010; 1842-2010; 101 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains church records such as vital statistics, committee records and meetings, minister information, auxiliary information and events, printed materials and annual reports.
  - Vital records, 1842 1960; 1842-1960; 4 Folders
    The Membership series includes records related to church vital statistics including members register,letters of dismission, marriage certificates and newspaper articles on marriages and deaths.
    - Orthodox Congregational Church register of members, 1842 1939; 1842-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters of dismission, 1939 1947; 1939-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Marriage announcements and obituaries, 1947 1949; 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Marriage certificates, 1952 1960; 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Committee records and meetings, 1842 2009; 1842-2009; 22 Folders
    This sub-series contains committee records, by-laws and society meeting reports.
    - Committee records and society meeting minutes, 1842 1883; 1842-1883 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Society meeting minutes, 1844 1855; 1844-1855 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Society meeting minutes and correspondences, 1856 1946; 1856-1946 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Committee records and annual meeting minutes, 1921 1927; 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Committee records and annual meeting minutes, 1927 1931; 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Church planning committee, 1947 1954; 1947-1954 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Committee records, 1950 1953; 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Canvas committee, 1953 1958; 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Committee records, 1954 1955; 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Committee records, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Committee records, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1957 1978; 1957-1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Board of deacons, 1961 1962; 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Committee records, 1962 1965; 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - By-Laws, 1970 2009; 1970, 1991, 1998, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Committee records, 1968 1970; 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Committee records, 1978 1983; 1971 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Committee records, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Committee records, 1973 1974; 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Committee records, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Committee records, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Committee records, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ministers, 1878 1989; 1878-1989; 7 Folders
    This series includes pastoral search committee records, installation information and records of Samuel C. Bushnell and Edward A. Morris.
    - Installations, 1878 1900; 1878-1900 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Minister Samuel C. Bushnell's scrapbook, 1890 1920; 1890-1920 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ministers, 1889 1940; 1889-1890, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Installations, 1915 1989; 1915-1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Minister Samuel C. Bushnell's scrapbook, 1916 1946; 1916-1946 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Pastoral Search Committee, 1968 1976; 1968-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Minister Edward A. Morris, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Auxiliary organizations and events, 1899 2010; 1899, 1937-2010; 11 Folders
    This series includes the records for church organizations and events, such as the annual Craigville retreat, Homecoming Sunday, Sunday School, musical events and the Pageant of the Brides.
    - Choir, organ and musical events, 1899 2010; 1899, 1973-2010 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Pageant of the Brides, 1937 1950; 1937-1950 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Education and Sunday School, 1956 1970; 1956-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Events, 1956 1979; 1956-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Church World Service Day and Cuban refugees, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Homecoming Sunday, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Craigville retreat, 1973 1978; 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Craigville retreat, 1979 1980; 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Craigville retreat, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Craigville retreat, 1982 1984; 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Craigville evaluations and registrations, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Historical Information, 1901 2004; 1901-2004; 13 Folders
    This series includes historical information such as church scrapbooks, newspaper clippings and anniversary material.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1901 2004; 1901-2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Church scrapbook, 1937 1952; 1937-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Church scrapbook, 1953 1954; 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Church scrapbook, 1954 1955; 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Church scrapbook, 1962 1974; 1962-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Church scrapbook, 1974 1978; 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 125th anniversary, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dedications for stained glass windows, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Silver appraisal, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Church scrapbook, 1986 1987; 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Church scrapbook, 1987 1988; 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Church scrapbook, 1988 1989; 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 150th anniversary, 1992 1993; 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Printed materials, 1901 2007; 1901-2007; 27 Folders
    This series contains printed materials, including church services, the newsletter "The Banner" and some older newsletters from before the start of "The Banner".
    - Church services, 1901 1934; 1901-1934 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Church services, 1936 1942; 1936-1942 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Church services, 1942 1948; 1942-1948 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Church services, 1949 1954; 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Church services, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Church services, 1956 1957; 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Church services, 1957 1960; 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Church services, 1961 1963; 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Church services, 1973 1981; 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Church newsletters, 1948 1950; 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - The Banner, 1967 1970; 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - The Banner, 1970 1972; 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - The Banner, 1972 1975; 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - The Banner, 1975 1977; 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - The Banner, 1978 1980; 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - The Banner, 1981 1983; 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - The Banner, 1984 1986; 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - The Banner, 1987 1989; 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - The Banner, 1989 1992; 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - The Banner, 1992 1995; 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - The Banner, 1995 1998; 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - The Banner, 1998 2000; 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Banner, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Banner, 2003 2005; 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - The Banner, 2005 2006; 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - The Banner, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Church services for children, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Annual reports, 1932 2010; 1932-2010; 17 Folders
    This sub-series contains the annual reports from Pleasant Street Congregational Church.
    - Annual reports, 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Annual reports, 1934 1940; 1934-1940 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Annual reports, 1953 1956; 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Annual reports, 1957 1959; 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Annual reports, 1960 1962; 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Annual reports, 1963 1964; 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Annual reports, 1966 1969; 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Annual reports, 1970 1972; 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Annual reports, 1973 1975; 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Annual reports, 1976 1977; 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Annual reports, 1978 1980; 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Annual reports, 1982 1984; 1982-1984 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Annual reports, 1985 1989; 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Annual reports, 1990 1994; 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Annual reports, 1995 1997; 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Annual reports, 1998 2004; 1998-2004 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Annual reports, 2005 2010; 2005-2010 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Financial records, 1855 1998; 1855-1998; 31 Folders
  This series contains information on church finances and the church building. This includes treasurer's reports, committee records, insurance information, property records, building purchases, building repairs and renovations.
  - Account book, 1855 1920; 1855-1920 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Financial records, 1882 1883; 1882-1883 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Financial records, 1923 1937; 1923-1929, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Architectural plans, 1947 1952; 1947, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Ruling on Mary A. Hill's will, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Property deeds and mortgages, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Property deeds and mortgages, 1929 1938; 1928, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Bequests and wills, 1941 1956; 1941, 1950-1956 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Church bells, 1948 1950-03; 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Property deeds and mortgages, 1949 1987; 1949-1955, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Loans, 1950 1961; 1950, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Church bells, 1950-04 1950-12; 1950-1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Selling of land, 1950-1954 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Church bells, 1951 1962; 1951-1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondences regarding construction project, 1953 1954; 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Parish house furnishing committee records, 1953 1955; 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Loans, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Church treasurer reports, 1954 1960; 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Building repairs, 1955 1972; 1955, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Parish house furnishing committee records, 1955 1956; 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Financial records, 1955 1958; 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Insurance Information, 1957 1958; 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Dr. Ralph B. Lancaster Memorial Fund, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Loans, 1961 1979; 1961, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Steeple renovation, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Schedule of rates for use of facilities, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Town of Arlington zoning and by-laws, 1970, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Financial records, 1970 1993; 1970-1974, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Inventory lists, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Existing conditions report, 1996 1998; 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Church bells, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Photographs, 1871 1999; 1871-1999; 14 Folders
  This series includes photographic prints and 35mm color negatives of church events, portraits, including ministers, and images of the church structure.
  - Church building, 1871 1959; 1871-1959 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Edith M. Fox, 1900 1980; 1900, 1955, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Events, 1924 1961; 1924, 1947-1961 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Damage from Hurricane, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Pageant of the Brides, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Portraits, 1950 1973; 1950-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Men's club minstrel show, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Content Warning
    Please note that this folder contains historical images depicting white people in blackface. The Congregational Library & Archives does not condone these racist depictions but makes them available to give an accurate and holistic portrayal of the historical record.
  - Parish house, 1954 1955; 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Friendship fair, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Communion silverware from 1807 at bicentennial service, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Arlington Town Day, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Craigsville Weekend, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Myron and Elizabeth Taylor, 1998, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Organist Heinrich Christensen, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)